All I would say is if stablecoins are inevitability at this point, and if you are building in FinTech
and or at a payment company and you aren't actively figuring out how do I future-proof this business
for stablecoins, you're going to lose.
Welcome to Bankless, where we explore the frontier of internet money and internet finance.
And today on Bankless, we are exploring the frontier of stablecoins. The stablecoin conversation
in crypto goes all the way back. You can find discussions of stablecoin concepts as far back
as the Bitcoin talk forums, which was the original venue for all of crypto's great ideas.
In 2025, the conversation continues. Stablecoins have been, and seemingly always will be,
an incredibly important part of the crypto revolution. Things are a little different now,
however, in 2025, things are no longer conceptual. The emergence of stablecoins like USEC and
Tether have grown into a $200 billion market cap asset class, and the performance of blockchains
have risen to match the needs of internet-based stablecoin settlement networks.
Because of these unlocks on the crypto tech tree, we are now finally seeing startups
weave together the old siloed financial system into new internet public blockchains.
And it's because of the utility value of stablecoins that so much progress
has been made over just the last year. Rob Haddock, the guest on the show today,
says that he is seeing 30% month over month growth of cross-border stablecoin volumes.
All of this, combined with the regulatory clarity and stablecoin bills that are passing
through the United States Congress, are creating a gold rush in the stablecoin economy.
Everyone is trying to get a piece of the incredible amount of value that is going to be produced
by the invention of stablecoins. It's also interesting to note that during the times of
Donald Trump's isolationism and rejection of globalism, that the crypto and stablecoin industry
represents an inherent interconnectedness since blockchain networks know no borders,
and stablecoin transfers are weaving together the global financial rails tighter than they've
ever been before. I just thought this was an interesting contrast that came to my mind
during my podcast with Rob. I learned quite a bit with Rob, so I'm sure you will as well,
so let's go ahead and get right into that episode. But first, a moment to talk about some of these
fantastic sponsors that make the show possible. In the Wild West of DeFi, stability and innovation
are everything, which is why you should check out fracks finance. The protocol revolutionizing
stablecoins, DeFi and Rolex. The core of fracks finance is fracks USD, which is backed by BlackRock's
institutional fiddle fund. Fracks designed fracks USD for best-in-class yields across DeFi,
T-bills and carry trade returns all in one. Just head to fracks.com, then stake it to earn
some of the best yields in DeFi. Want even more? Bridge your fracks USD over to the
frackstool layer 2 for the same yield plus frackstool points, and explore frackstool's diverse
layer 2 ecosystem with protocols like curve, convex, and more, all rewarding early adopters.
Fracks isn't just a protocol, it's a digital nation, powered by the FxS token and governed
by its global community. Acquire FxS through fracks.com or your go-to decks,
stake it, and help shape fracks nation's future. Ready to join the forefront of DeFi?
Visit fracks.com now to start earning with fracks USD and staked fracks USD, and for bankless listeners
you can use fracks.com/r/bankless when bridging to fracksl for exclusive fracksl perks and boosted
rewards. Uniswap is your gateway to a more efficient DeFi experience. With Uniswap swapping and
bridging across 13 chains is simple, fast, and cost-effective, helping you move value wherever,
whenever. Thanks to deep liquidity on the Uniswap protocol, you'll enjoy minimal price impact on
every trade, and now Uniswap V4 takes it even further. Swappers benefit from gas savings on
multi-hop swaps, and ETH trading pairs, while liquidity providers can create new pools at 99%
lower costs. The best part, you don't have to do anything extra. Each trade is automatically
routed through Uniswap X, V2, V3, and V4, so you give the most efficient swap without even thinking
about it. Whether you're swapping, sending, on-ramping, off-ramping, or bridging, Uniswap's
web app and wallet gives you the tools to unlock DeFi's full potential on Ethereum,
base, arbitrum, Unischain, and more. Use Uniswap's web app and wallet for a more efficient way to
use DeFi. Imagine verifying yourself without handing over personal data. No hacked databases,
no unnecessary personal exposure for air drops, and no AI bots ruining community governance.
Meet Self, the on-chain identity verification protocol built for privacy and control. Self-protocol
uses zero-knowledge proofs to confirm your identity safely. Users prove key details like age or
citizenship without revealing sensitive personal information. Self never stores your data. It only
generates cryptographic proofs. Here's how it works in three steps. First, register and verify.
Use the Self app to scan your biometric passports RFID chip. Self-verifies authenticity with
zero-knowledge proofs. Each passport creates one unique identity. Second, you can share proofs
privately. Third-party apps request identity proofs, like confirming your over 18. You can also link
proofs securely to public wallets for air drops or governance participation. And then last,
secure verification. Apps validate your proofs instantly on-chain, like on-cello or off-chain.
Audited by ZK Security, the Self app is live on iOS and Play Store. Visit self.xyz and follow
self-protocol on X. Bankless Nation, I'm here with Rob Haddock General Partner at Dragonfly Rob.
Welcome to Bankless. Thanks for having me. Rob, I'm going to start this episode by reading off
a quote and then maybe you can just pick up the trail right from there. Stablecoins aren't going
to be the best product for all forms of payment, collateral mobility, savings, etc. But they are
better and will continue to get better for many, many use cases, eating into that trillions of
dollars of the addressable market. Now, this is a quote from you. Maybe you could just expand on
that. And overall, it's just set the table for us when we get into the conversation of
stablecoins, where we are now, where things are going, and why people think stablecoins are just
such a big deal. Yeah, listen, the stablecoin topic is not a new one. People have been talking
about this for a long period of time. Circles exist since 2012. And there's been a lot of conversation
around stablecoins that I don't think has made a ton of sense. But what we've really started to
see in the last year is people kind of formulate or understand where are the places where stablecoins
are the most exciting. So when I put that quote out there, a lot of people I've talked about are
like merchant payments and stablecoins or domestic payments. And we haven't seen that adoption because
I haven't actually been particularly that excited about that type of use case. And in part because
stablecoins sometimes aren't cheaper, sometimes they don't have the right to level of compliance
on the right level of usability, or a better level of usability than call it traditional rails.
But what we have seen today is after things like cross-border payments, things like payouts,
just the want or desire to have US dollar access and emerging markets, things like being able to
use this as collateral for different types of trading or tomahly settle across different assets.
Like those things are all clearly much, much better in stablecoins. That market is trillions
of dollars. They are taking over that market. I think what people are learning right now,
especially with the election of the recent administration, which is of course much more
crypto-friendly, which means that we're going to get some crypto-friendly legislation
pushed through Congress, which is definitely the backdrop of why people are talking about
stablecoins right now. People are looking at how crypto is going to become regulatory compliant,
regulatory clear. And I think people are realizing that stablecoins are just a first step into
traditional finance, the rest of the world's foray into crypto. They're going to start.
The first stop on that train is stablecoins. And in addition to that, I think people are just
kind of looking around at all the stablecoins and realizing that the conversation doesn't end
at stablecoins. We are not ending the conversation at USDC or Tether. There is many, many, many next
steps for investment projects building out this stablecoin tech stack. Maybe you can kind of
pick up where that train goes. So we already have USDC. We already have Tether.
What are the few next stops on that stablecoin train that you are seeing getting built out first
and are the most interesting to you? Yeah. So I think it's helpful to maybe frame this as what
is a stablecoin? Because what I think in crypto happens is we talk a lot about stablecoins for
different types of products that are clearly not stablecoins or stablecoins for different use cases.
So you mentioned, Tether, very traditional treasury backed or almost treasury backed in
Tether's case, stablecoins that are meant to be for payment use cases. So you mentioned
the Genius Act or the stable bill layer here in the US. They specifically talk about these
payment stablecoins. Mika has the same thing, essentially. And there are things we talk about
in crypto that are stablecoins that are better for what I would call "collateral mobility."
So things that are potentially yield-bearing products that aren't meant to be moved a lot,
but are meant to be maybe used as part of a treasury operation or something like that.
Is savings vehicle? Yeah, exactly. Savings vehicle, same thing.
Then you also have stablecoins that are more crypto-native, that maybe are some sort of tokenized
cash and carry trade like an Athena or a part of that plus the USTB. So it's bidle,
where it's meant to be more of a savings account or a yield account, et cetera, for retail,
potentially, and institutions. And you have these different use cases, and we call them all stablecoins,
but they're really meant to be used for different things. And so I think you have to start there,
and then you have to say, well, what do each of these things—how do they fit in with different
parts of the market? On the payment side, I've actually written about that the most
fulsomely, but I actually think that's the part where we haven't seen a lot of pickup until recently.
So, Tether and Circle, it's over $230 billion outstanding today, but almost all of those use cases
traditionally had been just essentially trading pairs on decentralized exchanges and decentralized
exchanges. A vast majority of Tether has been on like Binance and centralized exchanges like that
over time. But just over the last year, now what we've started to see is the right infrastructure
for payments. And so you have things, and I wrote an article about, okay, what are the different
parts that you need of the infrastructure stack? But you have, now we have these orchestration
players like Bridge and Conduit. You have the settlement rails, so you have a lot of people
starting to talk about, okay, well, we do need a stablecoin native blockchain that does specific
things at the blockchain level that are better for trading traditional PSPs online. So,
codecs is one that we back. There's another one called Plasma that's talking about this.
You have some of these guys that are just trying to pull together like the last mile or APIs for
local currencies. And a lot of people in between now, we started to see stablecoin specific banks,
etc. But that infrastructure is now just good enough that I think what we're probably doing,
and this is kind of some proprietary data, but maybe $50 billion a month of like cross border
actual payments being done on stablecoin rails. And that's been growing extremely quickly,
20%, 30% month over month. But then 20%, 30% month over month in volume being transacted
across border and stablecoin. So that is incredible growth.
Incredible. Yeah. And it was basically nothing 15 months ago. So if you look at Bridge or Conduit
or any of these guys, they were $1 million of revenue last, call it January or 2024.
What happened over the last year was that these came into the mainstream, the infrastructure was
there, people were excited. And now you go and you talk to world pay or you talk to checkout.com,
you talk, obviously, Stripe, anybody, even like the coroner CEO tweeted, like, oh, do I need a
stablecoin strategy now? And the answer is yes. And every single one of them has a stablecoin
strategy today. Let me just trace over the conversation as I heard it. And you can correct me if I get
anything wrong. We're on using this metaphor of like we're on the stablecoin train and all the
stops on the train. The first stop is the stablecoin, the stablecoin stop. And I said circle and
tether and you expanded that to also include other types of stablecoins that even though that we call
these things all stablecoins, they are functionally different products. You have the true stablecoins,
the USDC, the USDT. I don't know if you want to call those the true stablecoins. But those are the
stablecoins that I think come to mind when people say the worst stablecoin. Payment stablecoin.
And then there's also like savings, vehicles, like Athena, where the yield coming from exchanges,
the way that the Athena works, there's a bunch of yield in the background that turns into a stablecoin.
And it has like a savings facility that really makes that work. Same thing with like MakerDAU
and the die savings rate. And so there's different, even though the product that comes out of these
things is a stablecoin, how that stablecoin emerges is kind of characterizes that flavor of that
stablecoin. But that's the first dot nonetheless. There's a crypto dollar, there's a synthetic
stablecoin that's out there that's produced and there's produced in a variety of different ways.
And the dollar just comes out of that as a token on some of those sort of crypto rails.
Yeah. And I would functionally put like Biddle in there as well. Even though it's not meant to
have a lot of velocity, it is theoretically like should be one to one swappable for a stablecoin.
Well, and it is too. It's actually in the Biddle contracts to be one to one
swappable with USDC. Yeah, that's right. And it is functionally used for now a lot of things
that stablecoins, the circles or the tethers used to be used for like the collateral ability piece.
And so I think if we hear City talking about or they actually have a tokenized deposit product
and some of the banks are thinking about that, all of these things at the end of the day have
different maybe like collateral or backing, but they functionally serve similar use cases and they
cross over. And I think it's good to segment them in that case when you think about, okay,
we'll invest in or what do I hold for what use case and also how the regulators think about them.
Okay, so that's the first stop. A true stablecoin, a token that is valued at a dollar.
And then I think what you said next is like, well, the next stop is payments. And that's
still kind of getting built out. There's still a lot left of juice left to be squeezed there.
And that makes sense to me, like when we talk about crypto, you know, speedrunning the history
of money and finance, we actually just start with a value. And then we figure out how to pass it
around at the second stop. But really just hanging on that first stop of all the different,
you know, taxonomy is the different ways of creating a stablecoin. How much do you think that we're
done on building out that first stop? Like, turns out, I don't think anyone really saw the novel
construction of Athena coming so late in the crypto game. I know still early. But nonetheless,
we found a new way to create a stablecoin that's incredibly valuable. How, how, you know, percent
completion, do you think we are done with figuring out all the different ways to build a valuable
stablecoin? We're like 5%. We're early. So listen, the payments market is humongous. And so when
you think about payments, it's $200 trillion that are done annually cross-border right now.
We are doing, I think, 50 billion cross-border on stablecoins. I think the reality is stablecoins
for that specific use case are functionally and unequivocally better as long as we solve the
infrastructure problems. So there's compliance concerns. There's making sure that we have enough
liquidity that costs come down. There's making sure that we have the last mile solved. But as we build
those things out, the vast majority of that, especially at the SMB market, which is about 40%
of that number, is going to be better served by stablecoins and stablecoin rails. I think wise
came out with a kind of a TAM slide in one of their kind of end of year reports, maybe like a few
days ago. I'm blanking on the exact number now, but when they put their TAM out there, they said
essentially it's like $50 trillion of revenue that wise thought that they could go and attack.
And I'm telling you right now, wise is a great business. It is a business that is
capital and efficient that requires a lot of interconnectivity with the banking system that
requires a lot of operational connectivity that would not need to happen if it was on stablecoin
rails. In that business, maybe they will do it themselves or maybe they'll be displaced,
but that $50 trillion would be better based on stablecoin rails, 100%.
Now, when you say 5%, are you talking about specifically payments?
Yeah. So I'm talking about the kind of intersection or the getting into the payment side.
I think on the savings account side, though, I don't think it's that different, right?
So you look at the emerging markets. Clearly, new bank is starting to add and
revelry it's been talking about adding stablecoins. And we hear a lot of conversation around this
from a lot of these different PayPal has it. But it's unclear to me yet that the majority
of new bank customers, it's definitely not true that the majority of new bank customers,
when they get a dollar in, it's actually being swapped to a stablecoin in maybe a non-custodial
manner and being able to use it automatically with other types of protocols or be able to swap
for other types of assets, et cetera. And so I think we're maybe further along, but in the
emerging markets, we're starting to see just a tremendous, tremendous amount of growth as well.
But I still think we're that far along. We're talking big numbers for crypto.
We're talking small numbers for the global economy.
Right. I want to just narrow the question back down to just the first stop on the stablecoin
train. The USECs, the Tethers, the USDSs that would formally die, the Athena stablecoin.
How much left and do you think is there room to make a new stablecoin, a new valuable construction
of a stablecoin? That was actually the original intent of my question. It's like filling out this
first stop on the train. Are we mostly done? Are we ready to leave and focus on payments?
Or is there still plenty of juice left to squeeze with a potential building out of a
new stablecoin construction? Yeah. So I think if you look at the business model of Tether and
Circle, Tether has essentially become an asset manager, an investment manager. If you look at
they continue to dominate in emerging markets, they continue to try to expand their influence
in those places. But they actually, Paolo was on all that yesterday and he's been running around
DC. So it's clear he's thinking about... He's going on the media tour, yeah. Yeah, it's clear
he's thinking all what's happening in the US and in Europe. But so far, Tether has not made
a compliant. If you look at the first iteration of the Genius Act, it doesn't look like Tether can
be compliant there. There's been news that maybe they'll have a segregated US version of Tether.
I frankly find that hard to believe that that would do well, because you have a lot of the issues
that just kind of a startup has. And it doesn't really have a great brand with the, called the
Regulators and the Regulated Businesses here in the US. So it kind of feels to me like they're
going to continue to dominate this one piece of the market, but I don't know if we'll grow into
the other parts of the market. And interestingly, I moderated a panel with Paolo in Dubai last year,
and I asked at the end to everybody, because all the others were challengers startups,
how much market share they thought Tether would have in five years. And the most bearish person
on the panel was Paolo. He said, I think we'll have like 35 or 40% market share at the time,
it was 70. Everybody else was like, oh, 70, like, let's continue to dominate. And I think he kind of
sees the world coming that he's not going to be able to really keep that moat with the current
business model. And that's why they are investing in so many other things and doing so many other
things. I think circle, same thing, you see it like they're starting to think more about payments,
specifically as part of their business. You know, you saw there, the rest one, there's clearly,
they're clearly giving away a lot of the economics, but they're hamstrung by that coin-based deal.
They're not able to potentially really kind of, I think, incentivize the way like a Paxos has
been able to with their global dollar network or some of the startups like Agora are able to.
So I actually think there are a lot of possibilities for challengers. And this market that's $230
billion of issue today, but that my guess is, you know, trillions or tens of trillions of dollars
after when it comes for the early dollar market in the future. Also, a lot of opportunity for
non-US dollar stable coins as we get a more robust FX market. So I think it's, you know,
it's definitely not 5%. But do I think that there are going to continue to be, you know,
challengers and that we might be in the, I don't know, netscape period of stable coins? Like,
I think that's possible. My next question is pretty related to this. It's just with the
incumbents that already have network effects. How valuable do you think those network effects are?
And so is Circle, Tether, we can even talk about coin-based and stripe here. I know, you know,
coin-based is stable coin is basically essentially USDCs. Stripe doesn't have a stable coin, but it
is a incumbent with network effects surrounding payments. How much new value do you think will
flow to incumbents with network effects versus how much do you, how disruptable do you think
that these incumbents are? Yeah, so there's no doubt there's a lot of network effects.
And I think the, you know, Circle and Tether are going to continue to be great businesses.
They're going to continue to grow. I think what we'll see a lot kind of will mirror the FinTech,
you know, boom of the early 2010s, where a lot of the challengers that grow will grow because they
grow with other businesses that grow with them, right? So if you look at Stripe, how did Stripe
become so dominant? They grew Shopify, right? They weren't the first one to offer e-commerce
payments. PayPal was already there. They offered a better experience. They got into Shopify.
Shopify blew up. They grew together. They were going to see some of that with some of these
challengers, but they're going to continue to kind of really entrench themselves on the coin-based,
the stripe, et cetera. I think there is a really big conversation to be had around all of these
startups that are doing things like call it stable coin orchestration, you know,
start calling themselves stable coin payment service providers, do stable coin banks,
things like that. I think this is especially true on the direct-to-retail FinTech side.
It's kind of unclear to me why a new direct-to-retail FinTech would win over a new bank,
just making its product better with stable coins and with, you know, DeFi on the back end,
where we've seen a lot of investment capital from a lot of the traditional firms,
the Sequoias and QEDs, et cetera, and the world go into those products because they're growing really
quickly. But in many, in a lot of cases, not all of the cases, they're growing because crypto
natives are looking for things to do with their stable coins. How do I spend it without actually
off-ramping? But it's unclear to me like why these traditional incumbents can't just,
you know, put stable coins in the back end and win. I think for like the banks,
now we talked about like on the banking system, the banks are kind of fucked. I think the banks
are fucked. Like they just move really slowly. They're not going to innovate. They're going to
do their own stable coins. It's going to be closed loop. It's not going to work. But at the PSP FinTech
side, I really struggle with the stable coin specific new startups. Okay. So now we're getting
a little bit further down the train of the stable coin journey. And this is will actually bring us
to the article that you wrote, which inspired this podcast to begin with. You wrote this article
called stable coin payments, who actually wins. And then you just listed out a variety of categories.
Maybe it's comprehensive. Maybe it's most of it. Maybe there's some missing categories,
but I'll just read them out here. Settlement rails, stable coin issuers, liquidity providers,
value transfer and money services, aggregated APIs slash messaging platforms, merchant
gateways and Rams, and then stable coin powered FinTechs and applications. When I was reading this
article, I was just kind of getting this idea of like this larger structure around stable coin
infrastructure. You know, you start with the actual token, you start with the stable coin,
and then you need to build products and services around stable coins to really expand the utility
around them. Maybe you can just kind of walk us through how you see that structure being built.
And really, as we go from, you know, stable coins to stable coin payments to some of the more
longer tail parts of the table coin tech stack, what parts of that tech stack really get you the
most excited. So the issue was actually came first. And well, the problem with stable coins for a
long period of time is they solve this problem, which was that nobody wanted to denominate their
on chain capital and their trading pairs, et cetera, with, you know, something that was also
volatile. But that's the only place that they were used. And, you know, kind of what we just
talked about right is they weren't really usable in any other way outside of crypto for until
recently, honestly, in any real way. You know, you listen out those categories. I would essentially,
you know, I don't think it's comprehensive anymore. There's some things I'm missing,
like, you know, banking where we've started to see that. But I think it is a good way to frame
most of what is being built. When I think about those different pieces, okay, well, you know,
you started the blockchain layer, the settlement layer, right? And so that's the most basic form
of what you need when you are with the issuer, what you need when you're transacting. And I think
there's a real question around, and I know you have specific opinions about this and some other
people have really strong opinions about this. But there's a real question around whether or not
general purpose settlement rails or general purpose blockchains actually serve the needs
of what, like, large-scale traditional businesses need if they're going to do trillions of dollars
across border payments. And so specifically talking about like, how do I bring a world pay
or a checkout.com onto on chain and then bringing the majority of their transactions on chain,
especially the cross border ones. I don't think that even the high throughput chains that exist
today, the bases, the salinas, et cetera, serve those needs. I think there's specific things that
they are never going to do, which they aren't going to get priority to these specific transactions.
They aren't going to help with any resistance for these specific transactions. There's not
going to be privacy at the transaction layer. They're not going to stop the launch of the new
mean coin that might just like make the RPC rollover. And so these things that happen that I think
you need a specific chain that is a network for these types of payments. That's highly debatable.
But we put our money behind that and see a few other people launching those. I also think it's
just true that they do fully verticalize the stack. So I talked to my article about how maybe that
orchestration layer doesn't have a lot of pricing power over time. But what if I can vertically
integrate the orchestration layer with value-added services like compliance, with the chain itself,
where I get sequencer fees, and maybe I have a government stoke in that all these people have
to stake to be part of that network. Can I give away the orchestration for free, where everyone
else is charging tens of bits? And I just make up that money on the back end by essentially having
them stake my token and pay sequencer fees. And so now you're starting to get really interesting
thought processes around how to structure my business, how can I price it, how can I incentivize
people to be a part of it. So I think that's kind of number one. Before we move on to number two,
could you just define orchestration layer? What does that mean? Yeah, so I think Zach Abrams
actually coined this. And he kind of reinvented the way people think about Bridge, which in many
ways Bridge was an on-ramp and off-ramp. But he called it an orchestration layer, which was just
a way to connect different ramps and different counterparties with APIs to transact on with stable
coins. Okay, so what problem is that really solving in the stable coin? Well, how does that
expand the utility of stable coins? Why do we need this? Yeah, so for that, right? If you,
what we talked about for a lot of these stable coin transactions are happening across border,
right? And so one of the biggest problems right now is that it gets hard to find liquidity if you
need a different, some sort of different effects. It's hard to find, you know, maybe the right ramp
in the right location, i.e., meaning like, you know, the biggest remittance market in the world
is U.S. to Mexico, right? One of the second biggest, I think, is U.S. to India. But actually,
both those markets today are doing over 9% of their remittance volume in stable coins,
which is actually humongous. But you have to be able to, like the end user, the receiver
in Mexico, they want to be able to receive that stable coin, at least historically, I want to
be able to receive that stable coin, bring it into, or it's been part of it into the local
currency, the peso, and then potentially put it into their bank account, right? So connecting those
liquidity providers as I talk about, connecting those ramps, those banks, those real-time payment
services in those local areas, you typically have to have like some sort of, you know, call it,
you know, API that allows you to do that. It requires usually a few different counterparties,
so you're essentially wrapping a bunch of APIs into maybe a single product, like what we're just
doing. There's one way to understand this. We have these financial servers in the cloud, right?
Bitcoin, Ethereum, Solana, these are servers. Blockchains are just servers in the cloud,
and they act as like a coordinating hub for everyone to point their, you know, for their
servers too. It inverts the way that we have banking, where Wells Fargo is a closed server,
every single bank in America is a closed server. Now we have these fewer servers,
where everyone can point their finance to it in the cloud, but we also still have
the rest of finance to deal with, which is still this like mesh network of siloed servers.
And it was maybe what you mean by an orchestration layer is bridging that gap between these new types
of financial servers in the cloud, Bitcoin, Ethereum, Solana, all these layer ones, and then
the many, many different types of siloed servers that actually do have like present boots on the
ground in these like local economies. And an orchestration layer just bridges that gap.
Is that a way to understand it? Yeah, I think that's a great analogy. The cloud is also a
really good way to think about like the adoption curve here and how we've kind of evolved.
Okay, so there's like with every single country, there's just like
kind of like a long tail of payments or banking relationships that we need to, you know,
enter, enter, operate with in order to make stablecoins on public blockchains actually,
you know, connect to local economies. And so that's what we mean by orchestration layer.
Yeah, and I'll give you an example here, right? So there's a portfolio company of ours that did a
payment from Brazilian Real, and they've been starting to do payments from Brazilian Real to
do Euro from your bank account in Brazil to your bank account in a European Union country,
where they are pulling using picks, which is basically like a real time, real time payment
business in Brazil, they can pull that capital out of your bank account in Brazil, they can swap it
to a stablecoin, typically US dollar denominated, or if they if you issue and have enough liquidity
for Brazilian Real, then they can swap it on chain to a Euro using, you know, maybe an M pool or,
you know, some sort of liquidity provider, and then using a separate instant in Europe,
immediately putting it into your bank account in Europe, right? But there are a bunch of
different people involved in that transaction liquidity providers in different countries,
banks in different countries, real time payment businesses in different countries,
but doing all of that through one API to that end customer and bringing that together and
transacting relatively cheaply in less than 15 minutes, the traditional banking market,
you know, maybe two weeks to settle. Right. So that I would imagine that this startup has a direct
call to circle, right? They are minting USCC directly, minting and burning USCC directly
as needed in order to facilitate that. And so what I'm seeing here with this orchestration
layer is actually abstracting away, which we all will always promised to do the blockchain world.
So the blockchains are just becoming increasingly transacted. The utility of stablecoins is becoming
increasingly expressed while also increasingly hidden. And we're just allowing people to do
things with their normal lives and experiencing the value of public blockchains without actually
exposing it to public blockchains. Yeah, that's absolutely right. I mean, the business is when
we're talking about like, you know, integrating ourselves with banks and like web to payments
businesses, they absolutely do not care about what chain they're on. They don't care about
particularly what stablecoin they're using unless they have, you know, OFAC concerns or BAS concerns.
They care about the fact that it happens quickly. It's cheap that there's, you know,
uptime and that the transactions don't fail, but there's good compliance and that you're adding
value to them and their, their own customers. And so if you can abstract that away and offer this
kind of integrated solution that uses all these different counterparties for better than what
they're having today, like they love that. Okay, so these, these orchestration layers,
I would imagine are going to change the topology of the financial landscape in these local economies,
because if their goal is to connect stablecoins to, you know, the every single citizen in Mexico
or every single citizen in an emerging economy, they need to, they need to generate that relationship
with the right banks or the right fintechs to connect users to stablecoins so that they can
connect it to the rest of the world. But I would imagine they, they don't need to integrate with
every single bank and every single fintech that's in Mexico or Argentina or any emerging economy.
They just need to connect with the one that like has 90% or they can cover 95%. And I think that
actually might expand the network effects of the dominant players in local economies.
And so we can start to maybe get more efficient by really just allowing the winners, the top three
winners of a local economy to just connect, connect into the orchestration layer, which
allows them to connect to a public blockchain, which allows them to connect to the other dominant
players in a different emerging economy and allow for that remittance network to just become
hyper-efficient. But I imagine this, this stablecoin technology is a boon to the already dominant
like banks and fintech layers in local economies. That's my intuition. Is that right?
Yeah, I would say that's true. The one thing I would say, or I would caution and we see this
in a lot of the people that are, you know, out kind of raising capital is that you have to do
hard things. And why do I say that? Building an API that kind of wraps other APIs today,
when Stripe did it, you know, over a decade ago, and it turned the banking system,
the e-commerce payments in the seven lines of code, that was novel. That was incredible.
And everybody was like, Holy shit, like this changes the market. Doing that today,
it's a lot easier and a lot more people can do that. Your modes are not as deep. And so to your point,
if you're a traditional player who is thoughtful enough and already has the connectivity and can
innovate or build a tech stack quickly enough or partner quickly enough, like you can probably
build those modes a little bit on the startup side. What we've seen is if you want to be able
to really kind of get into these markets, you need to do the hard things. And what are the hard
things? The hard things are dealing with the banks. The hard things are getting them comfortable
with your operations and your compliance and scaling them because the banks are the ones who
will say, Hey, listen, like, you know, you're putting too much volume through right now. We
think you're a high risk. We're going to limit you. And you just get you have to limit your
customers because of that. It's also compliance. Compliance and payments is actually very hard.
And it's a big part of the reason. Compliance and risk are the two reasons payments are expensive.
Not any other reason. And so being able to isolate that risk, underwrite that risk in a asset that
atomically settles, that's really hard still as well. And so if you can do the compliance,
you can deal with the banks and you can figure out how to front risk or be capital efficient
with maybe partnering with your risk. That is where we're seeing people build modes or maybe
startups where you might think the incumbents are able to do, but they haven't really quite
wanted to vulture their own business yet by by doing that.
What's an example of a stablecoin company that maybe you're like, the deck comes across your desk
and you're like, Oh, you guys are not doing any hard things. What's an example of an easy trap
for a stablecoin company to fall into? Yeah. So I won't name any specific names, but there's one
that comes out that I've seen the CEO kind of in a bunch of news and raised and raised some capital.
And they're kind of doing or they also talk about themselves as an orchestration layer,
what we're talking about, but they don't have any end relationships in any of these local
countries. They don't have any bank accounts within these local countries for client bank accounts.
They aren't able to do any sort of compliance themselves. And so what actually ends up happening
is the, you know, they might, you know, someone will connect into their API and then they'll
essentially get matched with somebody else also connected to the API when they want to go call it,
you know, Hong Kong to Africa. But they, those two counterparts that have to essentially be
onboarded with each other, even though that they're in the, they're, they're connecting through the
API. And they have to sign what is essentially a non-reliance agreement with that API provider
that says, Hey, listen, like we're not actually the ones doing KYB or compliance. And so like,
they're, they're essentially people are signing up for these products because like they're trying
to quickly add more geographies. But those types of products, we're seeing a lot of people build
those because they're like the easiest things to build. They're all going to get just like cut
out of the transaction flow as other people. They're too thin. They are too high up in the stack.
They're going to get superseded by somebody who can get deeper than them. Yes, that's our
community. Right. Yeah, that makes sense to me. Yeah. Like doing the hard things generally ends up
being the things that no one else wants to do. Yes. But it's, it's, and you see it in payments,
you see it in stablecoins, you see them crypto broad, they like people don't want to do the hard
things and then they get cut out of the, cut out of the value chain. Right. Understood.
Okay. That was, that was really helpful. I think understanding the orchestration layer,
I feel like that is where there's a lot of juice left to squeeze when it comes to,
to permeating stablecoins across the globe. And that maybe, maybe that's like the era that
we're in right now is this part of the payment tech stack and, and really the growth of crypto at
large is focused on this area specifically as we kind of like weave in the global economy through
stablecoins through public blockchains and through orchestration layers. Would you agree with that,
like general take? Yeah, absolutely. We, the first era of like stablecoin adoption outside of,
you know, trading like we talked about was kind of payouts to like local contractors.
So, you know, people who are, you know, contracting engineers in Latin America who would like much
rather to stablecoins and they're getting their, you know, essentially their pay in stablecoins.
That was kind of the first era with the, you know, of adoption, real world adoption.
We've seen some of that too. There's actually a well-known payments orchestration or stablecoin
orchestration business that is working with a, a web to PSP that is doing like an only fans pay
out. But as you can imagine, there's like only fans creators all over the world. They do tremendous,
tremendous amounts of volume in most areas of the world that aren't in developed countries.
Those creators actually won't stablecoins. And so that's actually been a huge boon for their
business. It's high risk, but you can, you can see this also permeated to TikTok and to every other
social media, right? That's been kind of the first era. But then what we've seen is a move towards,
okay, well, now these traditional fintechs, these traditional businesses now also wanting
and seeing a value add. And that's the number I mentioned earlier, 50 billion across border B2B
payments. That's, that's the number that was essentially zero, 15 months ago. And as now moved
into this tremendous growth era, and my expectation is that continues to grow at 20, 30% month over
a month through at least the rest of the year and in the next year. You said that that 50 billion
number was proprietary. How are you guys measuring that? Where are you guys getting your data from?
So we're pulling together a few different data sources. Also just reality is as we happen to see
probably most of the guys who race in the space. And so pulling together a lot of the data from
from the different companies. That's a little bit of a high end of of what I think it could be like
probably 30 to 50 on the month right now. But also like every time I talk about this number,
it's probably outdated. And so it's just growing so quickly. But it's clear that this is something
when you talk to any web to business, any bank now that this is top of their mind.
Imagine a world where your day to day banking runs on a blockchain. That's exactly what mantle is
building powered by a $4 billion treasury and poised to become the largest sustainable on chain
financial hub. As part of their 2025 expansion, mantle is introducing three new core innovation
pillars that bridge traditional finance with decentralized technology. First is their enhanced
index fund, aiming for $1 billion in AUM by Q1. It provides optimized exposure to Bitcoin,
ETH, Solana and USC complete with built-in yield opportunities. Next, mantle banking promises to
revolutionize global value transfer through seamless blockchain powered banking services.
Bridging crypto into your daily life. Finally, mantle X blends AI with DeFi to deliver an
intelligent user-friendly experience for everyone. And the best part is that this is all in addition
to their already launched products like mantle network ME and FBTC. Ready to step into the future
of finance? Follow mantle on X at mantle underscore official and join the on chain revolution today.
We may have already heard about Infinex. Infinex has, in my opinion, the nicest cross-chain swap
and bridge feature that you will find anywhere. It is called switch swap and bridge. And we're
going to show you what it looks like. First, we're going to log into my Infinex account with a
passkey. Now, there's no seed phrases in Infinex. There's just a one click set up with biometric
passkeys. But in addition to that, my Infinex account is fully non-casorial. So bam, I just logged in,
it was two clicks and I'm already into my Infinex account. So let's go make a switch. I'm going to go
switch my USDC that is on base. And I'm going to buy Barra chain, which is a completely different
chain. So we're going to switch this. I'm going to press that button. And then Infinex is going to
execute this order, this cross-chain order for me. And now it is done. But actually,
I'm not really feeling Barra anymore. So I'm going to go from Barra to penguins. I'm going to buy a
penguin on Solana. So I'm going from the Barra chain to Solana. See, no transaction signing,
no gas to worry about. You just switch across whatever chain that you want with Infinex. That
was so easy. Go check out Infinex and try your first switch today. I'm going to turn the conversation
to the layer ones or the chains that really support stablecoins, generally speaking. I think that the
first era of stablecoin growth really came from native DeFi usage, where we needed stablecoins
inside of Compound and then Ave, and then now Morpho just to facilitate stronger DeFi,
lending and borrowing, leverage, margin, all that kind of stuff that allowed DeFi to go and
take its next step. And then with Solana, you actually see the increase of volume over lowered
total supply of stablecoins. So Solana doesn't have that much total supply of stablecoins,
but punches way above its weight class in terms of volume. And you can kind of see that, well,
that's aligned with the architecture of the Solana network. But nonetheless, I think,
as you said earlier, there's just a lot of constraints that public blockchains have,
no matter what, about what is needed to really create a strong payments network in stablecoins.
And so now lately, so that's kind of the public blockchain side of things.
Lately, I've seen a focus on stablecoin specific blockchains, like call it stablecoin appchains.
Either layer two or even a dedicated layer one with some pretty serious trade offs,
permission validator sets, privacy at the layer one, which kind of rubs against DeFi and other
parts of what we know to make a public permissionless blockchain. But I'm seeing this next phase of
blockchain design, stablecoin focus blockchain design to be really trying to go toe to toe with
things like Visa and really optimize for maximum throughput and are happy to make very strong
trade offs to really lean into stablecoin and stablecoin specific uses.
Maybe talk about where you see chain design going in the stablecoin era.
Yeah, I try really hard not to be ideological about the way I invest. And even though I have
specific things that I might like to see in crypto, and I know you feel very strongly about this as
well, I think the reality is like businesses that are going to put trillions of dollars of
capital through these rails, they do not care about the things that maybe you got you and I
into crypto. They do not care. They care about liquidity. They care about pricing. They care about
being able to have a full application set that makes them easier for them to do their business.
They care about privacy. They care about potentially not having to be in the same pool as some sort
of oh, fact sanctioned, North Korea or Russia or things like that. And they care that their
transaction gets there on time when they expect it to be there. And those are the things they care
about. Now, there's a network effect and to your point around Solana that exists where you have,
okay, well, you have a lot of this other activity, you have DeFi. And that DeFi means that there
are more stablecoins already on the chain. There are already liquidity providers there.
There are already ways to potentially transact. And that alone should cause there to be some sort
of like lower pricing and sort of cause it to be essentially potentially easier for certain things
to exist. But what you don't have is you don't have the other things, the privacy at the blockchain
layer. You don't potentially have the concerns. And maybe you can do that in an application layer
around, you know, OFAC sanctions, BSA, stuff like that. You do, you don't have prioritization
of transactions. You can't pay gas fees and stablecoins. And so there's trade-offs to your point.
But those trade-offs are things that maybe you and I care about that the businesses themselves
do not care about. So today, what we've seen is mostly incentives have won, right? Like,
why did PayPal decide to really put their focus on Solana on day one? And I might get
hate tweets for this, but it wasn't because of the technical infrastructure. It was because
Solana has a fantastic PD team and they paid them a bunch of money, right? And the reality is like,
that is what we have seen from where these people have gone today is because they've cared about
the pricing and they've cared about, you know, having somebody that they could pick up the phone
and be like, this is not working for me. Like, help me fix it, right? And so those who, those
chains who have done that type of PD and that type of marketing and customer service, they're
the ones who have, you know, one kind of more of that flow today. And so if you can take that,
you can do something that's a little bit more centralized. You can put a full stack solution
together that allows you to innovate all the way through the chain, through the application layer.
Like, it's my opinion that for those use cases, people would rather deal with those chains.
So what do you think is stopping something like Tether or Circle making their own dedicated,
like high throughput chain? And you can kind of see this show up where Tether has Tron and Tron's
dominant activity is like Tether's transfer is still a generalized permissionless blockchain,
but at least it's moving towards that direction. And then Circle has base. Same problem. It has
other things too. It has other baggage, but at least it gets some of that throughput.
But you can see some of these shapes starting to start to emerge, but none of them have really
gone after building their own proprietary, like payments network. Like, why do you think that is,
or maybe it just hasn't happened yet? I think Mordecom and more to be public,
in some cases, that's like, like in Tron's case, for instance, you know, they've I think publicly
announced that Bitfinex invested in I think called Plasma. Obviously they have Tron, you know,
not in public yet, but I think they've invested in three other blockchains at this point. Like,
they're trying to get themselves closer to a lot of these chains where they think that they can
influence. But what they don't want to do is they don't want to isolate or alienate these other
places where they're also being used today, right? Like, if they try to put all, you know,
USDT flow on their own chain, what's stopping, you know, Binance and BSC from trying to put,
you know, kind of push USDT off BSC, right? And they don't want to potentially have this situation
where they're eating their own their own business already. And so I think what we've seen in circle,
you'll hear a little bit more about too, they're aligning themselves with with another chain. And
then they've also they're also kind of launching their own orchestrator. So they're really focused
on payments as well. And so what we've seen is these guys have wanted to have influence. They want to
be able to kind of be a design partner and figure out or optimize the chain for the use cases that
they want or go hand in hand with somebody to do that. But they haven't wanted to go so far into
like alienating the current use cases and the current chains.
What about any new projects that are building that don't have the baggage of their incumbent
business and are building a dedicated layer one or layer two or some sort of chain that's just
meant for stable coins and stable coins only? Are there any projects out there that you're
particularly excited about or are worth highlighting? Yeah, I mean, we just announced an investment
to a business called Codex over there. I think it was Friday that we announced it. Super excited
about that. Founders were serial entrepreneurs. One of them was the first employee at optimism.
Another one was a very successful web to entrepreneur working very closely with a number
of design partners who are going to be announced over the next month or two that will, I think,
solve some of these problems where they're fully integrated from the chain level to the application
layer to do some of these interesting things around designing their business around how the
products that actually looks for the end user. And there are going to be a bunch of actually
really interesting flow partners or launch partners who are doing some of the things we talked about
before who are going to be sending flow through their own kind of day zero. So we're really excited
about that. Is that a new layer one? Is that a layer two? What's some of the architecture look like?
Yeah. So the no layer two founder was, like I mentioned, the first employee at optimism. So
is that Liam? No, how many? Yeah. So he was there for a long time. And maybe he was the second
employee, actually. But there for a long time. And that's been, you know, that's what he knows
best. And so that's where they're designing today. And you know, kind of pushing the technical
limitations there as far as they can. And so this is the layer two that settles to Ethereum.
Yeah. Okay. And then there has been some of the deal flow that we look at bankless ventures.
There's just a lot of other layer one, even permission chains that are cropping up just to
become sort of like visa competitors. What do you think about these sort of design constructions?
The biggest problem for all of these guys is going to be flow on day one, right? So like,
how do you incentivize people to come on your chain? And it depends on, in some sense, like,
you probably you may want permission with validator set. Maybe you don't. But if you're going to do
that, you still need to have it be easily interoperable with other parts of crypto.
If you want to be able to bring, you know, USDC, USDT, other stablecoins on, you want to be able to
bring a bit of all those types of maybe USD, et cetera. If you're going to serve, you know,
call it not just, you know, B2B payments, but you're going to serve like a broad set of payments
that includes retail. So for me, it's always been about, okay, well, like, why is this permissioned?
If it is permissioned, is that do they have some sort of edge for how they're going to bring flow
here? My opinion has mostly been that if it's completely closed system, they will just be eaten
by visa visas, doing tokenized payments themselves. They also have, I think, all visa direct,
which by their centers has not done well by crypto standards has done very well in terms of the
amount of volume that, and that's kind of outside of their traditional network. So you have to be
thoughtful around what are the things you are doing. So, you know, I don't know which specific ones
you're talking about, but there's one I'm specifically thinking of that, you know, is really just a
centralized database, which if that's the case, and you have kind of none of the, I don't know,
the value add of being, you know, kind of on chain and in crypto, none of the transparency,
none of the ability to audit those transactions that I think is not particularly interesting.
A little bit too close to the old world.
Yeah, you're just too close to our older internet. Like, there's definitely a spectrum
of blockchains, obviously, right? But if you're really just saying, okay, well, I'm going to
create a web2 database, but I'm going to put it on blockchain. Well, like, we've already done
that with hyper ledger, and that didn't work, right? And so, but if you are saying, okay,
well, I'm going to build on a permissionless stack that is part of the super chain, and that is able
to have interoperability as people want to do expand their risk tolerance and do different
things, but also it can be do all of the best are going to be the best place for you to do,
just, you know, direct B2B transactions. That's where you start to get this, like, liquidity flow,
right? And this liquidity mode. So you prioritize those cost those customers, but you allow for
different types of transactions in different type of use cases. So what I do think is going to happen
is that risk tolerance will change over time. And a lot of these traditional guys over time
might say, okay, well, now I do want to do something with tokenized assets. Now I do want to do
something where I have, you know, my stablecoin or my tokenized asset be part of this, like,
regulated FXAMM, but then also potentially be used as collateral for something that's
permissionless on Jane as well. How do you see all of these different parts of this stack
collapsing together over time? If you go to Argentina and you look at the FinTech businesses
down there, they are doing both stablecoin payments and stablecoin savings. So you can get like three,
four or five percent on your stablecoins in this FinTech app, but you can also pay your friend too.
And that's actually just because some of these stablecoins and some of the yield sources are just
hooked right into DeFi. And that's because that's also where the stablecoins are. We're also talking
about this whole entire new growth of orchestration networks and other types of stablecoins and, you
know, payment chains. I would imagine as if you would just fast forward five, 10 years in the future,
a lot of this stuff has really consolidated to become really having some sort of singularity where
all of these, all of the utility here is really pushed into the same vertical. How do you see that
playing out? Will that play out? Will that be fast? Will that be slow? What do you think that looks like?
There's obviously a little bit of it now. I absolutely agree that we're going to see consolidation.
It's not clear to me at what part of the stack we're going to see consolidation today. I do think,
you know, the strike bridge transaction was obviously a harbinger for, you know, probably more
M&A interest from call it, you know, traditional payment service providers. You know, it's clear
that strike also they want to go from just emerging business to a network business. They also,
you know, just talked about becoming a bank as well. And so you're seeing like kind of traditional
fintech traditional payments kind of have that collapse between, okay, well, I want to be a tech
company and I want to be able to take risks because that's where a lot of the money is made. And how
do I kind of vertically integrate that and then and also add a lot of different capabilities where
I can again, you know, make more money as part of that. So I think we're going to see the web two
guys come in and buy some of these orchestrators, buy some of these local ramps, these last miles.
I think we're going to see these, you know, kind of a lot of issuance happen also at the call it
orchestration layer with these like PSPs, i.e. meaning like you're a strike customer and, you know,
Stripe has their like treasury product today. Well, Stripe will probably start to also issue a
stablecoin or also an RWA as part of their treasury product so that you can more easily manage like
your capital with, you know, stablecoin or stablecoin type products. So I think that issuance layer
is going to collapse quite a bit. And I also think you're going to start out to have to do
compliance specifically at the chain level or in the application stack where you control that
chain. If you're going to do kind of more regulated, like, you know, kind of long payments for these
large players. And so I expect we'll see most of the stablecoin fintech apps we've seen today.
Like I think most of them are going to fail. I mean, that's that's normal for startups,
but they're just going to have a hard time finding distribution relative to the people who exist
today. And then like the merchant gateways, the ramps, like those are really tough standalone
businesses and in traditional finance or traditional payments, those are like either small businesses
or they just we've seen actually in the 2010s, there's a lot of consolidations of like basically
PE backed stablecoin gateways and ramps that had verticalized software as part of them,
where they just rolled them up. And I expect we see a lot of that happening as well.
What do you think? I think you're already gaming this line. Banks are fucked. But maybe we can
go into that question specifically. What does this mean for old world banks? The banks, as we know,
the banks that I pay my rent from, the JP Morgan's, the Wells Fargo, even the regional banks. What do
you think happens to all of them? Well, I think regional banks are fucked for non-fifty reasons
too, just because we've seen this consolidation of G said's. But banks are not good innovators,
like that has always been true. So they're slow to the tech stack. The best thing that has ever
come out of bank is Visa. Visa was a kind of a bank consortium. They spun it out, but that was at
a time when tech just moved much more slowly than it does today. Domestically, banks are still going
to do an incredible job. Well, the real-time payment networks are coming or here, depending on
much jurisdiction you are in. They will be able to do real-time payments that are at the speed of
and cheaper than blockchain rails for a lot of domestic use cases. That's going to continue to
be true. But then if you look at the global macro market, right, like right now, the US is in the
midst of cutting ties or pushing away some of its allies. We are becoming more protectionist.
The world is coming more protectionist. At the same time, when we already have this like
interconnected cross-border banking system that is ineffective and doesn't work very well together,
my expectation is that becomes even tougher in this future protectionist world that we're seeing.
And if that's true, then all of this cross-border payments are going to go to stablecoin rails.
On top of that, what you have right now is you have a bunch of countries where their
local currency is inflating or people don't have demand for their local currency potentially.
But I think we can debate a little bit about what's happening with the US dollar this past week
and the 10 years this past week. But today, at least people still see the US dollar as the
reserve currency, and that'll be true for seeable. And that demand also means that these people,
they want US dollars. And at a time when US dollars are becoming more usable, so I'll give you an
example. We invested in an emerging market kind of payments, FinTech, stablecoin business,
that when they finally were able to get a card issued by RAIN, that meant that they could now,
and it's on the VC network, that those people can now pay for, it has an economy that wants
a lot of US dollar goods. They want Netflix, they want open AI, chat GBT, they want to import
a lot of US dollar goods. If they were to try to pay for that US dollar good through the traditional
banking system, today they would have to pay a 10% tax. Now if they pay with their stablecoins,
they're not. There's a regulatory arbitrage there. There's a question around how long that
regulatory arbitrage stays. But what's clear is for those young people and those types of payment
rails, they want more access to US dollars, US dollar goods, and things like that.
And that'll continue to be a big issue for local governments, local central banks,
who today have been really protective of their current currencies. I think, and this is a more
macro point, we might be getting into a world where the amount of currencies is just going to come
way down. And we're going to need to see a world where you just have somewhat of a currency
war between the dollar and the euro, and the renminbi. And a lot of these other countries,
their currencies are fucked. So not only is this kind of a harbinger of the end of times for
banks generally, but also for central banks, for currency issuing banks,
secularly. Yeah, I think so in a lot of these emerging markets.
Yeah. Yeah. Well, what about non-dollar stablecoins though? Because there's is a push for tokenized
euro tokenized like long tail developing country fiat. What do you think about this whole sector
of the of the conversation? So you absolutely need non US dollar stablecoins for FX, right?
And so 60% of roughly 60% of the global reserves of currencies are in US dollars,
the rest are in other types of currencies. And it's a roughly similar number for the amount
of transactions or the type of transactions that happen. What we have seen to date is that
you're there is need for a euro and we're doing the type of transactions we talked about before,
where you're going bank account to bank account and call it in Brazil to euro. But
at the end, people are wanting to offboard to fiat. And in the, I think the developed markets,
you're still going to continue to get a lot of that. It's the developing markets where people
have wanted to keep things on chain potentially, or in these places where there's like regulatory
arbitrage or you're doing things like trade finance, which are hard risk. I think we're
going to continue to see adoption of those stablecoins. I am not bullish on most of those non US dollar
stablecoins becoming things that people hold on chain. So maybe a few people that I talked about,
but I think when we're talking about the Naira, like people are going to do it because they want
to do this remittance or they want it to get usable. But in the future, they're going to hold
the US dollar or they're just going to offer up to their bank. So maybe is it correct to say that
dollar stablecoins will hold all of the market cap while the long tail of fiat,
you know, African fiat currencies, developing country fiat currencies, they will exist simply
as a accounting tool in the foreign exchange world in the FX. Maybe there'll be high volume for local
payments, maybe not. But they're mostly there just as a utility token, truly to get the utility
out of their denomination so that they can connect local economies, local developing market economies
with the rest of the stablecoin networks on public permissionless blockchains, which are all going
to be dollar denominated. Would you agree with that general summary? Yeah, that's my expectation.
I think what you said utility token is a really good point. And so they're either going to want
US dollars and they're going to get that their stablecoins or they're going to be using some
sort of local as my expectation. Okay, final question, final, like kind of as we wrap this up,
how many different stablecoins do you think that there will be? Well, every bank issue a stablecoin,
everyone's going to try and issue a stablecoin. I feel like that's kind of the hot tweet that
could go viral right now because everyone's into this idea of like everyone's getting a stablecoin.
And I think it's very reminiscent of everyone's getting a layer two and we all kind of know how
that turned out. What do you think about this conversation? It sucks.
So I put out like a tweet like a week or two ago. That was basically like, listen, if this is not
your core business, like use somebody else to do it for you. I think what could happen is like,
okay, well, we think there's a million stablecoins, but it's actually like Paxos or Agora or Braille
on the back end. And they're all like interoperable with each other. I do think we're going to see,
at least for a period of time, a bunch of people be like, I need a stablecoin. And we're starting
to see this too, where people are like, Oh, I need a stablecoin, but it's only going to be for
internal use, because I'm essentially basically, it's essentially using as like a money market fund.
Well, like you could also just buy Betel, right? In the same thing, I don't know why you wouldn't
just do that in most of these cases. And so there's going to be a lot, I think, will a steady state
get to like maybe like on the US dollar side, like five to 10 that gain any real scale?
Feel like we already have five. There were real scale, the US dollar, but like, oh,
I guess what would you call scale? And yeah, okay. Good point. Okay. Circle tether,
die maker dows, die Athena. Maybe there's one I'm missing, but I guess you could argue that
maker down Athena or not really any sort of real scale in terms of marketing.
Yeah. Well, I think there's scale and further specific use cases with like, you know, on chain,
but when I said that I met it more as like, call it like the Paxos circle tethers, like,
you know, few others that are maybe more used in traditional payments. I do think like,
there's definitely still room for like crypto native, like, you know, savings and investment
products that have stable coins linked to them to do really well. The reality is like, die is
pegged to the US dollar because of what they decide to put in their collateral like they could
have completely changed all of their collateral from day one and it would no longer be a US dollar
stable coin. So yeah, listen, I think there'll be a lot in the near term. I think we'll see then a
lot of consolidation after that. And then what I do think we'll see is we'll see a lot of
basically interoperability because people are using the same service providers on the back end,
but they decided to brand it for whatever reason because people are narcissistic.
And I think it's good marketing as their own stable coin.
So when you see a stable coin project deck come across your desk and like the opening slide is,
we're going to make a new stable coin. Do you open that up with like cynicism with optimism?
Like what's your first emotion when you see a new stable coin project?
So I open up every deck with cynicism, but yeah, absolutely.
Today, I think like if you're doing like a new stable coin issuance,
like there has to be a really good hook and a really good reason for why this new thing has
to exist because you're so far behind all the competitors.
Okay, just kidding. One last question before we wrap this up. Circles S1, I'm sure you took a
look at it. What stood out to you in the S1 and then broadly, what do you think the circle IPO will
just do for the stable coin game? Yeah, so the circle S1 was was about what I expected.
My opinion on circle has continued to be that they are really hamstrung by that coin base deal.
And not only are they hamstrung by that coin base deal, we've seen them try to grow into like
binance and to other sort of distribution partners by paying them a bunch of money.
And so they just have to continue to do that. And that's how they've eaten in to tell there's
market share. But it means their margins are going to come way down. And what it means is that
potentially the public markets aren't going to like what their revenue composition looks like,
and they're not going to trade as like the tech company or the payment company they want to.
I think that's the debate, right? So there was this headline around though,
they had four to five billion dollars was the potential value. People were surprised by it.
I wasn't super surprised by that because the revenue model today looks like a asset manager.
And I think it's very clear over time how they don't just continue to get squeezed on their margins
themselves. They have to build out more of a payments business if they are going to get
the value that they want. And if they are going to be valued on a multiple like they
tried or somebody like that, which is I know is what they think is appropriate.
The second question, I guess, around what does the world do for the market? It'll be humongous.
So like, you know, and I do think the one argument against what I just said about them trading well
will just be because everybody knows stablecoins are eating the world. And the public market investors
will only have one way to express that. And it'll be buying that equity.
So let's simulate hypothetical universe where tomorrow you wake up and you are actually in
Jeremy layers seat and now you are calling the shots of circle. What are the first obvious
decisions that you make about how to lead the company? Yeah, so it's a good question.
Super hard question. I do not have to answer that.
I'm going to get a call from Jeremy's office. Do you post this? But no, listen, I think they
need to continue to focus on other lines of business. They need to figure out how their revenue
mix changes. They need to figure out a way to not have that Coinbase distribution partnership
be so such a drag on their business. I don't know if they can get out of it. I don't know
any details there, but they need to become more neutral in my mind over time. The Coinbase deal
made sense when they did it because that's how they boot strapped to that distribution.
Now it is a drag on their business. And so how do they figure out a way to improve the revenue
composition to add other services around it where they can monetize and how can they figure out a
way to not have Coinbase take 60% of their their top line. Those are the things that I would be
focused on. So yeah, so circle just really maybe they wouldn't characterize it, but like did it
deal with the devil where they gave a part of their revenue to Coinbase in trade for distribution
and in trade for growth. And that worked for the time that they needed it. And now what you're
saying is like, well, now that non neutrality, the fact that circles beholden to Coinbase is
preventing them from finding other markets, because now they're branded as like the Coinbase
stable coin. And the lack of neutrality is preventing them from expanding into like alternative
distribution models. Yeah, it's absolutely centered the growth. I mean, they've what they've done on
with Binance has been actually incredible. And like, congratulations, chairman, my team,
like they, but we do know that they paid them 60 million bucks and are also giving all of their
eel that they can to Binance to be able to do that. And you know, maybe that will again be
a deal that's that's worth making. And I do think it probably is. But you know, they're in a situation
where they have to give 100% of all circle revenue that's derived from USDC on Coinbase to
two point base, and then 50% of all other revenue. How do you go and build other, you know, distribution
partnerships at scale over time when this goes from, you know, the amount of issuance they have
now and it goes 10x from here if they're continuing to be in that that type of deal. And so like,
it was the right move to get them to hear how do they get from here to 100x from here or 10x from
here. I think it has to change. And I think it'll be really hard for them to continue to do so with
with that weight on their their shoulders. Rob, this has been definitely one of the most informative
podcast episodes I've done in a while. So I really appreciate you coming on and educating me and
educating the bank station. Thanks so much, David. This was this was awesome. Really appreciate it.
Yeah, maybe just one last like time just to know no specific question just open-ended stable coins.
Maybe just give us your your broad thoughts or conclusion your your bullish rah rah as we end
things really what other sectors that I haven't asked about are getting you excited or any remaining
thoughts that I just haven't asked. All I would say is if stable coins are inevitability at this point,
and if you are building in FinTech and or at a payment company and you aren't actively figuring
out how do I future prove this business for stable coins, you're going to lose and you need to you
need to figure it out and you need to come here and you need to ask me or any of any of the other
people who are really smart about this. That's a perfect way to start the risks and disclaimers
for this episode. Rob, I really appreciate you coming on Bankless Nation. You guys know the deal,
crypto is risky. You can lose what you put in. You can also lose if you are not paying attention to
what's going on in stable coins, but nonetheless, this is a frontier. We're glad you're with us
on the Bankless journey. Thanks a lot. Thanks, Dave.